It's my pleasure to
welcome Jan from OpenAI.
He leads the
alignment team there.
And he was previously a
researcher at DeepMind as well.
Holds a PhD in reinforcement
learning theory,
has been thinking about the
alignment problem for over 10
years.
And today, he'll be giving
a very interesting talk.
So I hope you guys enjoy.
Yeah, thanks a
lot for the intro.
And Thanks a lot for having me.
I'm very excited to
talk about this stuff.
I'm also super happy
to keep it interactive.
If you have questions at any
point, please interrupt me.
And yeah, I wanted to start
out with a few very basic
observations on what
I think is going on.
And so the first one is
Team AI is joining the game.
So Team AI have a lot
of different players.
They all joined
at the same time.
But rather, they
joined one by one.
And not all-- their players
are varying a lot in how good
they are.
And right now, a lot of the
players that have gone so far
aren't really that
smart and usually can
do it on a very narrow
set of [INAUDIBLE]..
But one thing that
we've kind of observed
is that over time, we're
seeing stronger and stronger
players join.
And this is kind of
where we are now.
And then in general, we
expect that Team AI has
some incredibly strong players.
So those will be
players that are
able to think so much
better than humans,
so much faster, and
so much more cheaply.
And these haven't joined yet.
And so the kind of anchor
point that we have,
if you think, for
example, about ChatGPT,
ChatGPT can already beat any
human at knowing more facts
or speaking more languages.
And it can write about
And it can do so about 100
times cheaper than humans
could at a minimum wage.
And so there's the--
ChatGPT also has some really
important limitations.
And there's a lot of things
that it can't do yet.
But it is kind of an indicator
of some of the players
that be able to
join in the future.
And so it seems like
in the long run,
Team AI will have all the
advantages over team human.
But-- and there's one-- there's
an important caveat, which
is there's one important
advantage that humans have,
which is Team Human gets to pick
which players from Team AI join
and when.
And so this is kind of an
advantage that we should really
be leaning into when we're
thinking about what to do
and when we're thinking
about this game
that we're playing with Team
AI and that we'll be playing
with Team AI in the future.
So I think two of the
main objectives of what
we as Team Human
should do is first,
we should try to recruit
players from Team AI
to play on Team Human.
And so this is kind of what I
would broadly call alignment.
And this is kind of like the
problem that I'm working on.
And then there is
also other objectives.
So another objective
that I think
is going to be
really important is
you want to write
the rules of the game
so that Team Human doesn't lose.
And right now, Team Human
kind of has the ball.
And we get to write the rules.
So we should write
rules that make sense
and that we'll play
this game in the future.
And so in this
talk, I won't really
talk about the
second point at all.
And I will talk
about the first point
because that's what I know.
That's what I'm working on.
And perhaps to phrase
it differently,
or to make it more
practical, one way
I'm thinking about
alignment is we
want to build systems
that follow human intent
and that follow human
preferences, that
do we want them to do.
And so a bunch of the
things, basically, I'll
talk about two main things.
The first part is going
to be work that we've
done in the past, and kind of--
which roughly is
in the bucket of we
are trying to figure
out how we can
make the models that we have
today as aligned as we can.
And you just try and--
try hard to do this,
and we'll see how far we get.
And then the second
bucket is the things
that we have to do next, the
stuff that we haven't done yet
that we think are going
to be really important.
And I want to kind of
lay out why I think
they're going to be important.
So now, I said I'm trying to
make this more clear, or more
broken down, what
alignment means.
[INAUDIBLE] here, because
now, the big question
is, what does it mean
to follow human intent?
And two main categories of
content that we care about
is, I would say,
explicit intent,
if you give the
system an instruction,
or if it want it
to be my assistant,
it should be my assistant.
It should follow
the instruction.
But then there's also
all these other intents.
And I don't say,
when I'm usually
talking to a system or a human,
that I also really care about.
It shouldn't literally
always do what they say,
but the thing that I mean.
It shouldn't make up stuff.
And it shouldn't
do harmful things.
And it should ask
follow-up questions
when it's not sure what I
mean, and so on, and so on.
And so these are
all kind of things
that are often just really
difficult to precisely specify
or precisely [INAUDIBLE].
But it is still things that
we want to get AI to do.
And then we have to figure
out how to get into it.
And so kind of like
the main technique
that we're using today for this
is what we call reinforcement
learning feedback.
So that was used to train
InstructGPT and ChatGPT, which
are the two main systems
I'll talk about in this part.
And basically, the basic
system is very simple.
And it's also like a
super general technique
that applies to lots
of different AI models,
and modalities, and settings.
But in this case, it
will be the [INAUDIBLE]..
And so two steps is actually
another step of [INAUDIBLE]
to stop for the
sake of simplicity.
First up is you want to train a
reward model from comparisons.
So you have [INAUDIBLE] in
this case, explain [INAUDIBLE]
field.
Or help me with my term
paper, whatever it is.
And then the model
does a bunch of things.
And then you rate which
one is closest to the thing
that you intended
the model to do.
And so you have a bigger
set of preferences.
And you're training one model.
One model basically just
[INAUDIBLE] which one would
you prefer.
Everything OK?
I would say I just
stand more in front
of the camera as possible.
Sorry about that.
Maybe let's try [INAUDIBLE].
OK, so OK, so now we
have this reward model
that captures kind
of our preferences,
and what we care about, and what
we intend for the model to do.
And then the second step is now
you optimize the reward model
with the reinforcement learning.
And so not that a--
the model tries a whole
bunch of different things.
And the reward model tells
it which one of these things
is probably more like the
thing that [INAUDIBLE]..
Yep?
When you say
comparison, does that
mean by a human labeler
goes in the data?
Yeah, and all [INAUDIBLE]
that depends on the label?
They will depend on the labeler.
Different labelers will
have different preferences.
They also might be
inconsistencies.
And you can give examples
in front of the preferences.
But those haven't really
been a problem in practice.
And so far, our labelers
often don't agree.
But the model will
average RL [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah, so this is like
the basic technique.
It's conceptually
like quite simple.
You can make it
even simpler if you
didn't train the
reward model and you
labeled every [INAUDIBLE].
But it would be a lot
less data efficient.
And so you could--
training a reward model
to think of a data [INAUDIBLE].
So how will it work?
So this is kind of like
one of the main thoughts
from the InstructGPT paper.
And it's the one that I'm
sharing because it really
blew my mind.
And it still does.
What do we see here?
So on the x-axis, you see this
is one of the PP3 model matrix
and you see this is three
different types of models
over two orders of magnitude.
And on the y-axis is
how well does the model
score on human preferences.
So if you show a bunch
of samples to humans,
how likely are they to
prefer one over the other?
And then what we see is
that even the largest PP3
model is dispreferred to the
smallest InstructGPT variant.
And so the 100x
smaller Instruct model
is actually preferred over
the much larger [INAUDIBLE]
like GPT, [INAUDIBLE] model.
And that's kind of wild.
Let me just finish my thought.
So why-- why is
this [INAUDIBLE]??
So basically, it basically shows
that they would [INAUDIBLE]
be on the line [INAUDIBLE]
making it a whole lot more
useful than giving [INAUDIBLE].
Or fine-tuning works, then
nobody want to use it.
And make all these fancy
alignments techniques
that don't get adopted.
And so what we were--
originally, in
the first version,
we saw these regressions.
And then what here
is labeled PPO,
PTX is kind of like a very end,
where we mix in pretraining
data into the fine tuning.
And that mitigated a bunch of
the regressions that we saw.
Yeah?
And I just had a quick
follow-up to that.
How important is like fidelity
on fine-tuned that you have?
You guys, you collect
data from humans, right?
What if you were to
use some pretrained
[INAUDIBLE] model
to score [INAUDIBLE]
or something like that?
Yeah, you could do that.
And there have been
other papers on that.
A topic wrote this
paper on [INAUDIBLE] AI
was trying to exactly do that.
In terms of-- well,
there are certain things
that the language model will
be able to automatically rank
and some things that
won't because it won't
know your exact preferences.
Or it won't know exactly
what we want it to do.
And so whenever the language
model does something
that we disprefer,
we actually-- we
have to give it
another data point.
Or in other words, if
you're aligning with humans,
you somehow have to put
humans into the loop.
So that otherwise,
how does the model
know what you are
supposed to do?
Lots of more questions, I
don't know who was first.
Yeah?
How many-- approximately
what's-- how many orders
of magnitude of human
preferences do you need
to achieve these--
Yes, I'm going to get
to that in a second.
[INAUDIBLE]
So why did [INAUDIBLE]?
We haven't actually
compared, carefully
compared across
all our algorithms.
And it could very well
be that a different RL
algorithm would be better.
That was kind of like--
I know, PPO was invented OpenAI.
So that's why we used it.
It's not really a good
reason other than that.
It works also pretty well.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Comparisons, this better
than this sort of thing.
So usually, we
have people compare
between three to six
different responses
from usually different models.
Yeah.
So is PPO and the reward
model currently used
in ChatGPT in production?
And if so, do you use any
of the human feedback,
you regenerate responses
and stuff like that, so--
as a reward function as well?
How do you mean to regenerate?
There's a button
on ChatGPT where
you can say
regenerate responses,
or do you use any implicit
feedback, basically in humans?
I don't know what the
current state is for that.
I expect people
will try to use it.
But ChatGPT hasn't
been out that long.
Yeah.
So I'm curious about this graph.
But it seems like
increasing parameters
doesn't give you
that much more like
fidelity there.
Qualitatively, you have been
tracking this for a while.
Can you tell right
off the bat if you're
like interacting with a one--
model or the 100 billion model
like a pseudo Turing test
with parameter size?
I give you a--
see on how many
parameters it has?
Probably not very precisely.
But I think the big
counterquestion is do I
get to write the prompt?
So if you just
draw random prompts
from whatever people put in
the OpenAI playground, which
is what we use for
InstructGPT, then I probably
need quite a few to
tell the difference.
But if I get to
write the prompt,
I can probably do
it in one or two,
at least if the task is tell
the difference between this
and this.
I want to-- can I just do
two more slides and maybe
your questions get answered?
And then-- so this was the
question about training costs.
So this is another thing
that kind of really
blew my mind is
compared to pretraining,
it is incredibly cheap.
So if you look at the amount
of laps that it takes to train
GPT to [INAUDIBLE].
And then you compare
it with how much
the fine tuning and
the pretraining works
and everything, the most
expensive InstructGPT variant
is less than 2% of the
pretraining compute.
And if you want to train
an even bigger model,
it's going to be more expensive.
And you could still use
the same fine tuning step
to make it more aligned.
And of course, I think
the important thing
to note also here is we
haven't fixed all the problems.
There's important limitations.
And so I wouldn't say that
this is the last version.
And we wouldn't
try to figure out
how to spend more compute and
more human data in the future.
But all in all, it was
surprisingly effective.
OK, there were more questions?
More questions?
Yeah.
I just wanted to ask
what the PTFs were.
Mixing pre-training
data into the fine tune,
just like mix the gradients.
Yeah?
What's the number
practice for this graph?
So you're fixing
[INAUDIBLE] for this one?
So this is the full
size GPT-3 version.
So this is the
Questions?
No.
OK.
[INAUDIBLE]
Great.
sure, so the first one is--
OK, sure.
So the first question
is, how would you deal
with [INAUDIBLE] in the limit?
Example preferences are
a good proxy for values.
But optimizing for
them just [INAUDIBLE]
to incentivize research.
Yes, I'll get to that.
Sure, that's the next question.
So that is like you want to
automate [INAUDIBLE] research,
what happens if we need
conceptual big tools, which
are difficult for
experts to verify?
OK, that would be good to
take at the end as well.
Sure, let's see.
Sorry.
I guess one question is how
would find getting better
on human feedback compared to
fine tuning of [INAUDIBLE]..
Fine tuning-- like
supervised fine tuning?
It's more like if you actually
use the human [INAUDIBLE]..
I'm also not sure
what they mean.
So I mean, so one
baseline was showing here
is what if you just take human
demonstrations in the sense
that we have a bunch
of tasks, we just
ask humans to do them,
record what they did,
and then train the
model to imitate that.
And here, it's like just very
basic behavioral cloning,
just using the same laws
they use in pretraining.
And then it's noticeably
better than the future
prompted version.
But it's still
not as good as RL.
And so that's why
we like using RL.
And basically,
conceptually, there's
two problems with the
imitating humans approach.
One is humans are better at
some things than the model is.
And they're worse
at other things.
And so the things that
the model is worse,
you're trying to imitate
something that you can't do.
And on the things where
the model is better,
you're making the model
worse because you're
forcing it to do the thing in
the way that the human would.
And so with RL, you
kind of-- with RL HF,
you're kind of letting the
model do whatever it wants to.
And it can just figure out the
best way for it to do things.
There's also another
important advantage.
And I'm going to get to that.
But I briefly I want
to talk about ChatGPT.
So one thing-- I kind
of think of ChatGPT
as like the upgrade
to InstructGPT.
It's kind of like the
next step at making
the models more aligned
and more useful to humans.
And some things that I
think Chat does better
is using dialogue as
the universal interface.
You can talk to it directly.
You can ask follow-up questions.
You can ask it to refine the
answer and all of these things.
That makes it a lot
easier to deal with.
It's better at
refusing harmful tasks.
But it's also-- there's
still important limitations.
The biggest one is like the
model of hallucinates a lot.
It makes up facts when--
for whatever tasks you give it.
And that makes it
quite unreliable.
It's also still sensitive to
prompting which kind of shows
that it still has
important misalignment
that we need to fix.
Really, if a model was like--
models should really do the
task to the best of its ability,
no matter how you
prompt it to do that.
But yeah, one important
principle that I think
is really useful for--
or that [INAUDIBLE] on
a lot is that evaluation
is easier than generation.
So if we ask humans
to compare and rank
different responses
the model gave,
it is easier to
tell the difference
between different variants
of what the model did than it
is to do the task itself.
Or in other words, you can
do the comparisons on tasks.
You can still spot
good behavior on tasks
that you might not be
able to do by yourself.
And so if you're giving
this kind of feedback,
that lets the system do better
than you actually could.
And I think that's a very
general principle that
holds in lots of domains.
So kind of like you're
probably most familiar--
[INAUDIBLE] you know
that P versus NP.
And everyone-- we don't actually
know whether they're different.
But in practice, it seems like
NP tasks are just much harder.
It also applies to
lots of other settings.
A lot of professional
sports, so e-sports just
wouldn't be fun to watch
if you couldn't tell who's
winning more easily then
you could actually compete
on a professional level.
It applies to a lot
of consumer products.
You can look at two smart
phones and tell which one
you like more without--
that is also deeper than
just looking at the specs.
That is actually pretty high.
But it's my phone.
It also applies to
academic research.
It's much easier to review
your paper and say what--
all the things that are
bad about it than it
is to write a good
paper yourself.
It applies to-- I don't
know, when you're--
yeah, basically, there's lots
of domains where this applies.
And so I think this is a very--
this principle is
very useful when
we want to align AI systems
on tasks that we might not
be able to do ourselves well.
So having said that, RL HF
has some really important
limitations.
And I think that's going to
make it really difficult to use
our RL HF to scale alignment.
Let me explain this
with the diagram.
So basically, on the x-axi,
let's plot the AI progress.
And on the y-axis, how
difficult different tasks are.
And then as we have more AI
progress, kind of like the task
that AI--
the difficulty of tasks
AI can do goes up.
And one of the
fundamental problems
is that the level of tasks that
humans can reliably evaluate
doesn't go up.
Because humans don't get
better with AI progress.
And so I think we're
somewhere here.
But the problem is once
you cross this line,
you don't really know whether
your model is actually
doing the right thing
because you can't reliably
evaluate it anymore.
And so that's kind
of like the point
where RL HF training
will start to break down.
And what we'll probably see
is what the question before
alluded to is like,
well now, the systems
are optimized for whatever
feedback we give them.
And so they will
try to tell us what
we want to hear, rather all the
things that they to be true.
And they might learn
how to deceive us
because that makes it easier
to score high on preferences.
And so kind of the basic
idea that we want to leverage
is related to the
principle I just mentioned,
which is evaluation is
easier than generation.
So for example, if you have a
large language model writing
a code base, an
entire code base,
there's just no way humans would
be able to find all the bugs,
and all the flaws
in the code base.
Or the code base could
have a Trojan in there.
And you might not be able to
tell because it is so hard.
And that's why we see so
much buggy code out there.
But if you ask your language
model to find bugs and point
them out to you, once
you've seen the bug,
it's so much easier for you to
say, oh yeah, this was a bug.
Please fix it.
And so now, you've taken the
task of [INAUDIBLE] code base
down to, well, I
just have to evaluate
whether that was a bug according
to the spec they had in mind.
And so the general principle
that we are excited about here
is we want to
leverage AI assistance
for human evaluation.
And so the hope is
that we together, we
pair up humans with
AI, you actually
get a line that looks more like
this, where humans together
with AI can evaluate
much more than they could
by on their own.
And so to make this
concrete, there's
like two different
ways you could do that.
Or there's many different
Two I want to highlight.
First, you can write-- ask
AI to write a critique.
This is a project
we did last year.
And in this case, it was a
simple summarization task.
And we trained a language
model to kind of just
say things that are
wrong with the summary.
And there's other
things you could do.
For example, you can give
people ChatGPT and ask them,
OK, use ChatGPT to
help you evaluate.
And then you could
ask for a critique.
Or you could ask for
a lot of other things.
You could ask for
an explanation.
You can ask for a fact
checking, or a quote,
or whatever the model ChatGPT
can actually reliably help you
with.
And so the idea would be that
like using AI assistance,
you can kind of get all the
smarts that AI has and leverage
that in order to figure
out how you should evaluate
what this system is
doing and whether it's
aligned with your
preferences or whether it's
trying to deceive you.
And the big problem
with this is how do
we know whether it's working?
And one of the difficulties
is that by assumption, we're
kind of dealing with
a hard task where
it's difficult to evaluate.
And we also wanted
the task to be
a real because we want to solve
some task that doesn't matter.
And so it becomes--
So you need like a
hard task that is real.
But also if you have
those, you usually
don't have ground truth.
So you got no issue
with the right answer.
And how do you know whether
assistance is working
or it's biasing everyone
to just say the same thing?
And so there's a simple
technique that we use
[INAUDIBLE] to do this where--
that we call targeted
perturbations.
And so what you do is you
have a bunch of prompts.
So this could be like whatever
people type into ChatGPT.
And then you kind of take the
response that you have and say,
this is the correct response.
It doesn't actually
have to be correct.
But let's just assume it is.
And now, you're asking
a human to introduce
some kind of subtle flaw
that is easy to miss
but is an important flaw.
And now, what you have is
you have this paired dataset
of a good response
and a bad response.
And you know which
one is good and bad
because you made it worse.
And so in a way, that
gives you ground truth.
And so what you now can
do is you can take--
randomly select one-- either the
correct or the flawed response,
and then show it to
either a human or a human
with assistance.
And then they have
to say whether it
was the correct or flawed one,
or how good the response is.
And in this setting,
we can figure--
just try a lot of different
AI assistance or scalable
oversight techniques.
And then say is this
actually helping
humans find the flaws that we
planted more likely than not?
And if it is, then you're
actually really helping.
And so we did this in
the critiques paper.
So this is training the language
models to read critiques
and for summaries.
And what we can show is that
when we're assisting humans
with critiques at
the evaluation,
they actually find 50% more
flaws than they did without.
And so this is kind of
like real signs of life
that you can already use in
models that we can have today
to help humans evaluate
and find problems
they would have
missed otherwise.
And of course, we still have to
do this on a much harder task
and with a real
task, in a sense.
And we also want to have
a bigger effect size.
But I think it's
just like, it shows
that there's promise of these
techniques already working.
And so in the long run, what
I think we want to get to is
we kind of want to leverage
AI for all the cognitive labor
that goes into evaluating
whatever our AI systems are
doing.
And this could be like reading
everything that's relevant,
or fact checking, or doing
calculations, or writing
code, or any of these things.
And then humans should focus
on their preference input.
Like the things, figuring out
what they actually care about,
and what they want
the model to do.
And in this way, we can
leverage the abilities
that the AI players will bring
to the table, and the things
that they will be better
at than us eventually.
And then kind of like use
them to help communicate
the thing that we
actually care about
and the things that we
actually want them to do.
And yeah, that's it.
But yeah, those are
the main slides.
So I'm happy to
take more questions.
[APPLAUSE]
Yes?
I was wondering about this
hallucination of responses.
Have you ever tried to consider
some notion of uncertainty
in the answers?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] attempt to evaluate
variance between the responses
and [INAUDIBLE] the uncertainty.
So on some things it's
difficult because either you're
training--
fine tuning a sample
from a pretrained model.
And so you don't get that
much variance in your sample.
Or you're pretraining a
bunch of different models.
And now you're spending a
lot of money on pretraining.
One thing-- I mean,
it seems like it
should be a solvable
problem to just teach
the model to say it's uncertain
when it's actually uncertain.
And there's been a bunch of
research in that direction.
But I think, right now,
it's still like-- we're not
really in a good shape.
There's more stuff to do.
Yeah?
Do you think we may run into a
kind of signal-to-noise ratio
problem when it comes to AI
suggested critiques to AI
answers?
Because sure, when AI is trying
to point out potential problems
with text, humans are more
likely to report more problems.
But what if it's mostly
problems that humans
wouldn't have necessarily had
a problem with to begin with?
Yeah, so we did try to control
for that a little bit by having
humans rate the
severity of the flaws
and whether they would have
noticed them otherwise.
It can still see a
significant effect.
But also, I mean a lot of the
time, the model is nitpicking.
And then those are not
the interesting cases.
Also, if you're like look
at the example I showed,
which I think is from the blog
post, a lot of the critiques
are just actually quite garbage.
And one of the things
that makes it easy
for critiques is it's
OK for the most of them
are garbage because
the human can just
read them and discard them.
And it kind of more helps
evaluate it and know
where to focus on or notice--
think of something they
would have missed otherwise.
So it's more like
the critiques help
you brainstorm how you
should evaluate or something.
But if you're
using an assistant,
you probably want
more reliability
than most of the
answers [INAUDIBLE]..
Yes?
How do we ensure that
the valuation metrics
we are using in your recursive
reward modeling approach
detect deception, or
left turns, or something?
Do you have major discontinuity?
Yeah, I think-- well, it depends
a lot what kind of community
you're talking about.
If you get overnight a
model that is, let's say,
a number of parameters,
or equivalently better, that
can create quite a step up.
And that makes it
quite difficult
to do this kind of evaluation.
So in that sense,
I think it's going
to be very important to
scale up AI more continuously
and do more incremental steps.
Having said that, I think the
basic picture with request
reward modeling is that you're
training the systems to help
you evaluate--
systems that are trained or
fine tuned from the same system.
And so if you can
figure out how to get--
fine tune them in a way
that they mention everything
that is actually
useful and relevant,
then it would still be
able to evaluate systems,
even though they are much
smarter than anything
you've evaluated before.
Maybe let me make
this more concrete
because I think a way that you
could measure that, or like one
way we've tried it was using
what we call the discriminator
critique gap.
So to measure that,
you're training two
different-- you're fine
tuning to different models
from the same pretrained model.
One is the
discriminator that says
is this the flawed response
or the correct response,
or a more correct response?
And the other one is
a critique model that
tells you what the flaw was.
And now, you can measure how
often does the discriminator
get it correctly?
And the discriminator is
just like q gradient descent.
It doesn't have to want
to tell you anything.
You're just basically hooking
into the model's presentations
and trying to get all
the relevant insight
it has to this prediction task.
And then on the other
side-- other hand,
you have this critique model or
this general assistance model.
And you're measuring how often
does the assistant actually
help me point to the right flaw?
And then if you compare
these two scores,
you can look at the
gap between them,
hence this generated-- sorry,
discriminated critique gap.
And then if the gap is
large, then the model
knows a lot about the
task it's not telling you.
And so that would
be very worrying.
And if the gap is small,
then there's much--
presumably, there's fewer
things that the model is not
telling you.
But I guess there's
lots of value
like ensuring this
approach is robust
and testing it on
current models?
That's right.
That's why you want to
test it on current models.
Yes, I don't know who was first.
I think someone in the back.
So I wanted to ask
about the previous slide
where, it's like [INAUDIBLE].
So I couldn't help but--
part of that also
it's communicating
what you want the AI to
do, not just evaluate,
but communicating perhaps,
I would like you to do this.
And maybe [INAUDIBLE] that.
And so like at least like in
my personal experience using
the ChatGPT, there
are some things
that could do that without
[INAUDIBLE] surprising.
But [INAUDIBLE] to the
terminal, for instance, or you
can ask about [INAUDIBLE].
These are different
things where I'm
like, OK, what can I ask for?
And what [INAUDIBLE].
One thing that I thought
was a bit concerning
which just this idea that
people don't always communicate
their preferences honestly.
Or there could be
coordinated efforts
to instill words for
specific capabilities,
a coordinated effort
to do such a thing.
One idea I had for
this is I tried
to ask if that has like some
idea of a Wikipedia for itself.
I didn't know how
to use it at first.
So I just thought that--
[INAUDIBLE] there
didn't seem to be one.
I was hoping there was one--
there was one for GPT-3.
[INAUDIBLE]
And so my question is like--
how do you make that
sort of thing safe?
How do you recognize
coordinated efforts
to specifically reward
certain kinds of behavior,
maybe like some group
decides that they would like
to give it some capability?
So this is a--
yeah, this is a
really good question.
And in a way, I mean,
the first obvious thing
that you shouldn't do is
you shouldn't just literally
train on the data that people
give you using the interface.
And we've kind of seen
other examples of what
happens when you do that.
If you think of like
Microsoft K or something,
that can go pretty wrong.
The other thing is, I
mean right now, what
we're doing is we're
hiring a bunch of people
and then ask them to rate
different model responses.
But also, now, the question
becomes who are we hiring?
And what's their background?
What are they trying to do?
And so in particular,
the thing, I think,
we're doing quite
poorly right now
is actually importing a
diverse and representative set
of human preferences.
And it's more just whoever
we end up we can hire.
And so I kind of
wish there was also
this more targeted research
on how we should do that
and how that could be done well.
And some of that is also
like better placed outside
of big tech companies.
Because if you're-- tech
companies always have
an incentive to import human
preferences in a way that maybe
is not the thing
that we actually--
humanity would do under
reflection or something.
And so I think it's a really
big important question.
Does this [INAUDIBLE]
data contamination
is like the dual
problem to this?
Do you think the internet
might [INAUDIBLE]??
Probably is.
Yeah, I mean--
Is that something--
People might-- anyone
can poison the future
anyway, just post
something on the internet.
And it's something that we
have to be very mindful of.
Yes?
I don't know.
[INAUDIBLE]
Considering that we're
currently training these models
for [INAUDIBLE],,
those things are--
hopefully getting closer
to human preferences
at this point.
As human preferences change,
as we've seen [INAUDIBLE],,
is there something--
is there a paradigm?
Is there a way you can make
sure the model's keeping up
with data better?
What are your
thoughts around that?
Yeah, I mean, the
most obvious thing
is like the model's
knowledge base
is kind of like the
pretraining cutoff date.
Whatever data you
went into pretraining,
it doesn't know
about a lot of things
that happened after that.
In terms of updating
kind of human preferences
or the comparisons that
go into the reward model,
we just collect more
data and we train.
The functioning run is
like comparatively cheap.
So you can do that again.
I think what gets
harder is that as you've
deployed the model and
people started using it
for all kinds of
tasks that they want
to build their company
around, if you update
and you change the
model, then they also
have to do a bunch of work
into adopting their prompts
to whatever they're doing.
And so it doesn't
come at a zero cost.
Yes?
Sorry, you.
So on the note of exceeding
human performance.
One of the advantages
of GPT-3 is
that it has this immense
corpus of basically
the entire internet.
If you want to specialize
in specific domains,
like chemistry, or material
science, or something, in
[INAUDIBLE] generate new
content, then [INAUDIBLE]
be adapted to use less data
and still run as efficiently?
[INAUDIBLE]
You mean like less data on the
chemical domain or something?
Yeah, you may just have
the research papers
over the last 30
years or something?
Yeah, and you can throw
them to pretraining.
And then the model
knows about it.
Can the model really
manage effectively
without so much data?
Can it be-- that the abstract
concepts behind GPT-3,
[INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, I mean, that's kind of
the general idea with what you
intend to do with fine tuning.
And to some extent, we've seen
it generalized in this way.
For example, InstructGPT
was trained almost entirely
on English language
feedback and demonstrations.
And it works in other languages.
And so that's kind of wild.
And so similarly, you
could train the model
with people who don't know
anything about chemistry.
And then it learns to
follow instructions.
And it will do so on
the topic of chemistry.
And this fine tuning can
be very sample efficient.
With 100 data points,
you can actually
make a meaningful change
in the model of behavior.
So it can be quite effective.
I'm going to pick
someone hasn't asked.
Yes?
Regarding response
generation, do you--
or how much effort do you put
on [INAUDIBLE] the emphasis
and training of different
expression styles?
So what I've noticed from
ChatGPT, that it always
gives back structured
or scientifically
structured answers.
Do you consider in the
training if [INAUDIBLE]
scientific research to
answer or [INAUDIBLE]??
Yeah, I mean, the
tricky thing is ideally
the model should give
you the kind of answer
that you want to have.
And some people prefer more
scientific or technical
answers.
Some people might prefer
a more generic answer.
And I mean, right
now, ChatGPT doesn't
have a way for you to set like
your specific preferences.
And that's something that would
be really exciting to have.
But also I think the kind of
statistic property that you've
observed is, in fact, probably
a product of our labeler pool.
And so a lot of the
ChatGPT workers were more,
I think, more like
computer sciencey.
And more-- there was like more
data generated by programmers
compared to InstructGPT, which
was more generalist labelers.
And yeah, there's different-- it
kind of changes also the style.
So there is no specific
effort to distinguish
them, but [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, I mean, we should
make a distinguished effort.
It should give you the
style that you want, right?
Yes.
So one of the things that I've
been thinking about recently
is how ChatGPT is going to
play a factor in the education
realm.
[INAUDIBLE] coming generation.
And if you go back to the
graph of the AI progress,
the human level,
[INAUDIBLE] evaluate.
What I'm starting to think
about is for a grade,
I had to use [INAUDIBLE] I
showed my 10-year-old cousin
how to use ChatGPT, just
to mess around with.
And that green line
is a lot lower.
And furthermore, if
this becomes part
of their educational experience,
it's going to be much--
I perceive it to be
more difficult for them
to discriminate even simpler
tasks than what they do now.
And so I'm already
thinking about how
that might disrupt or make
this a little bit more
difficult in the long run, as
you have people who are more--
take for instance,
what ChatGBC--
sorry, ChatGPT says as
a hidden truth, anyway.
I was just wondering what
your thoughts are on that?
I mean, there's a real
risk of overrelying
on a tech that is
immature and that is not
ready for you just believing it.
Please don't believe
everything the model says.
But also I think
one thing that I'm
hopeful for is that like
your cousin will end up
figuring out how to do this.
Where they grew up with
all of these AI tools
that are getting
better and learning
how to actually leverage
them productively, right?
And it's kind of
like 20 years ago
or something, when you were
using Google Search much
earlier than
everyone else, you're
probably going to
get better at using
that as a tool for
everything you want to do.
More questions?
I think you had your
hand up for a while.
The slide where human tasks
and the chat task and the model
task.
Oh, the last one?
Yeah, so right now, it seems
like you guys are using humans
as biological sensors for the
real world, the physical ground
truth, and using language
as a compressed interface
to that ground truth.
Are you guys also looking
at using sensor technology
directly with your models to
get a more truthful answer of--
Yeah, I mean, it depends on
what that sensor could be.
I guess one of the most
straightforward things
is you could ask
the model to browse.
And then they can fact
check its own answers.
And it can import
external knowledge
that it didn't remember.
And yeah, I think that
would be quite useful.
I think that would be quite
useful for a sustained human
evaluation.
[INAUDIBLE]
You can look at WebGPT, which
is a published work on using
the model for browsing.
I think-- so one thing that
makes it harder when you're
using these external sensors,
or if you're letting the model
interact more directly
with the real world
is that it raises
more safety questions.
If you let your language model
make arbitrary API calls,
then you have to be
a lot more careful
with which calls it's allowed
to make and which is it not.
And if you're-- as opposed
to if you're just reviewing
everything the model says, then
you can decide which ones you
want to make.
So yeah, it's an open problem.
OK, one more question.
I think you didn't.
--about the reasoning
abilities of these [INAUDIBLE]
language models.
I've seen many
different people talk
about how there's only a fixed
amount of compute for token.
While in humans, they have
system one or system two where
we can just speak quickly
versus actually using reasoning
and think through things
that take more effort.
And then I'll see how that works
to try to use the [INAUDIBLE]
to achieve prompt, or
the chain of reasoning,
or [INAUDIBLE] step by step.
So do you think that's
sufficient to do everything
that's the level that we want?
Or will it require
real big fine tuning
or architectural changes?
I don't know.
I'm also the wrong
person to ask.
I'm mostly not trying to
get the models to have
new capabilities and
more like getting
them to play on Team Human.
And oh, do we want to
do the online questions?
Sure, yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] question.
So what do you think is
the [INAUDIBLE] from,
especially if you have
human [INAUDIBLE] chat bots
is happening more
than human infections.
So do you think the InstructGPT
could be more open arrow?
Yeah, quite possibly.
I mean, yeah, as
you point out, there
is a lot of conversational data.
And if you can use
it, that would be--
it should be useful.
I think broadly, you can
categorize this kind of thing
as like let's make the
RL algorithm better.
And I welcome the feedback.
And I think that's valuable.
And that should help us make
the same pretrained models more
aligned according to the human
preferences that we collected.
But also, you would still
run into all the limitations
that RL HF has.
Someone wants to [INAUDIBLE]
GPT model, OpenAI [INAUDIBLE]..
I think there's a fine
tuning API for GPT-3.
I don't think it
offers RL right now.
But it's supervised fine tuning.
So you could do like--
you can distill best of m and
do this kind of expert iteration
RL.
[INAUDIBLE] questions.
So the first question
could you more clearly
describe the pretraining
process for GPT?
Example, starting with
the x [INAUDIBLE] 001,
and then [INAUDIBLE] offering
data [INAUDIBLE] like that.
Sorry, I didn't catch that.
Start with text
image 001 and then--
How much user data
[INAUDIBLE] and how many steps
are there, that kind of things?
I think the exact
numbers are not public.
It's basically similar
to InstructGPT.
And for the InstructGPT
numbers, we had,
I think, around 50,000
comparisons and probably
like 10,000 demonstrations,
or maybe tens of thousands.
I don't remember
the exact numbers.
So I had this other slide with--
yeah, I was like about 20,000
hours of human feedback.
That's what I calculated.
[INAUDIBLE] feedback.
Because that's-- you can
get 1 million or whatever
[INAUDIBLE].
I mean, the big question
is how do you make--
how do you ensure quality?
[INAUDIBLE] models that can
create that out, or give
rankings or something.
But it's the whole problem.
That assumes you
already have the reward
model that you trust.
OK sure, so next question,
I think, that also was you
want to automate
around the search, what
happens if you need conceptual
[INAUDIBLE] experts to verify?
Yeah, so I mean the kind of
like ambition of that plan
is to train to model
that can do this kind
of conceptual research.
And you can picture
that a language
model that writes an alignment
research paper that we know we
read.
And then we're like, oh,
this is a really cool idea.
We should try this.
And I think going
back to evaluation
is easier than generation.
I think it also applies
to alignment research.
And I think, at
the very least, I
find it much easier to evaluate
alignment research than I
find it to produce it.
And so while there might
be conceptual breakthroughs
that we need that we
couldn't even evaluate right
now because they're just like--
if we saw them, we'd
be like, what is this?
And this is kind of like--
this is the reason why we
want to do scalable oversight.
Because if the language model
produces this really brilliant
insight and we can't even
recognize it at the time,
we should be able to have an
easier time recognizing it
if we use AI assistance.
And if we leverage like our
best AI models to figure it out
whether or not that was a good
idea, what is the weaknesses,
and what are the strengths?
And what kind of
experiments should we
run to know whether
this is a good idea?
And so yeah, I think
basically, the story
of just using RL HF to train
a model to do good alignment
research, you have
the obvious pitfalls,
which is the model might write
an alignment proposal that
kind of looks good to us but is
actually not a good proposal.
And it creates the AI that
is misaligned with humans.
And so in order to distinguish
the two, which might
be really hard, maybe it's not.
But I think we should
expect it to be really hard.
And then leveraging AI
assistants to evaluate that
seems like a really
promising plan.
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, that was my whole point.
It's not sufficient.
[INAUDIBLE] But do you think--
do you need something more?
Or [INAUDIBLE] don't
you think if you
can get a lot of feedback data?
Will that be sufficient to
get a better generation?
Or are we seeing more
behaviors that are missing?
I mean, the general, or like--
I think the-- basically, the
vast majority of the models
capabilities and
all the cool things
you see it do come from
pretraining, and not
from the fine tuning stage.
The reason why people sometimes
attribute it to the fine tuning
stage is that you didn't see
it in the pretrained model.
And the reason--
I think the reason
that we didn't see it
in the pretrained model
is because the prewritten
model was so misaligned, it
was not trying to help you.
And it was not
trying to show you
all the cool things it can do.
And instead, it
just regurgitates
a bunch of random web text.
And that's not what
you're looking for.
And so yeah, I think
what RL HF basically
has been doing is unlocking
capabilities that were already
in the model and making those
available for humans to use.
And in some ways,
alignment research
is very dual use in
the sense that, a,
if you have really good
alignment techniques,
you can use it to align with
whatever values you want,
including values that we
wouldn't particularly endorse.
And b, it also--
if you're doing
alignment right, it
will always look a
little bit like you've
made the system more
capable because before, it
wasn't really trying
that hard to help you.
And now, you've made
it more aligned.
So you actually see these
capabilities or already had.
Sure, [INAUDIBLE]
question before.
How would you [INAUDIBLE]
project that's [INAUDIBLE]..
So it's not like--
[INAUDIBLE] to
incentivize deception.
So how we counter that?
Yeah, so that was what I
was talking about here.
This is the whole
problem that we have
where what humans can
evaluate is constant.
And so we won't be able to
evaluate sophisticated attempts
at deceiving us.
And that's why we want to
do a scalable supervision so
that we empower humans to spot
these attempts of deception.
Familiar plans for conquering
[INAUDIBLE] stand up
to [INAUDIBLE] in a
word, could be changing
[INAUDIBLE] AI assistance?
So I think these
are real worries.
And to some extent,
we kind of have
to test empirically
how difficult
and how severe
they actually are.
I think so my personal
stance right now is something
like I think trying to get the
outer alignment signal really
right is going to be
And once we have that, then
a lot of the other things
might also fall into place.
So for example, I
mean, it kind of
depends on which startup
in a misalignment
you're worried about.
But one story is you kind
of training your system,
and it learns how to do--
it learns, basically, a
bunch of inner optimizers,
kind of like meta
reinforcement learning.
So for example, GPT-3 can
do like in-context learning.
And that's a kind of
learned optimizer.
And so now, you're doing
RL HF training or whatever
alignment training you have.
And you're like--
then optimizers
learn to do the thing that
you want on distribution.
But now, if you have a
distributional shift,
and this distributional shift
could be auto-induced, meaning
the model is causing it itself.
Now, you've got an
outer distribution,
all these inner optimizers try
to optimize for something else.
And one way you could like--
and you know, how much
that would actually happen
in practice is kind of unclear.
But one kind of more
important question
is if you have a really
reliable outer alignment signal
and you have this general
training signal that you trust,
you can also use that
on the new distribution
to train the system to be more--
or to get these inner
optimizers in a row, basically.
And so then you've reduced
the inner alignment problems
to how do you deal with
a distributional shift.
And how do you construct
an outer alignment signal
that you trust?
And those are problems that
we have to deal with anyways.
But yeah, I don't know how it's
actually going to shake out.
But it's important
open questions.
So regarding alignment,
a lot of the problems
that we're encountering
[INAUDIBLE] there not
much interest, it
seems, in explaining why
from these [INAUDIBLE].
I was wondering if
there's much interest
in the OpenAI for
[INAUDIBLE] these models
and explaining why [INAUDIBLE].
arbitrarily.
I mean, that's
definitely a [INAUDIBLE]..
As to why [INAUDIBLE],,
judgements.
Have you all been able
to interrogate the model?
I mean, I think where
we are right now
is pretty dissatisfactory.
I mean, you can ask the model
why it gave a certain response.
But you don't know whether
it's answering truthfully.
And you can also--
I mean, another
thing you can do is
you can give the
model its own response
and ask it to find out
flaws, which is what
we did in the critiques paper.
But I think the--
I mean, there's
one version where
you try to make that better.
But then the question is what
is your ground truth signal?
And I think better
angle of attack
is probably interpretability,
where you figure out
how to look inside the model
and then how it actually works.
That's what I'm asking about.
The level of research
on interpretability,
it seems as though that's
been really [INAUDIBLE]
such a high pressure space.
Your current thinking is moving
towards [INAUDIBLE] reducing
dimensionality effects of
reputation something that
can be [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, I mean, we are
working on that problem.
But I don't think
we have anything
that like-- to show right now.
And so it seems, generally,
not to be a very easy problem.
But I'm hopeful that
we can do some things.
I think in general, the problem
of interpretability or using
interpretability for
alignment is kind of tricky
because I suspect it's
going to be neither--
it's going to be not sufficient.
And it might not be necessary.
So any amount of
interpretability
you can leverage would
be useful because it's
another tool in the toolbox of
detecting deception or knowing
what you said, how--
why the model gave
a certain answer
and made a certain decision.
But it is kind of
unclear if you really
get really good at
interpretability
how you then leverage
that for alignment.
Presumably, you could
look in the model
and just throw
all the models out
that you can find
a misalignment in.
But then aren't
you just selecting
for models that
have misalignments
that are really hard to find
with the interpretability
tools?
Sure, just [INAUDIBLE] because
reason I ask about that
is standard practice
in a ethical journal
is that you have to put an
explanation on [INAUDIBLE]..
And I guess my
question is like--
why would you think
interpretabilty would not
be necessary?
Yes, so why would
it not be necessary?
So again, this is kind
of like an open question.
But basically, what stance you
could take is that at the end
of the day, what really
is going to matter
is the decisions that the
model actually takes and not
the reasons why it took them.
And so if you can
get to the point
where you're confident that all
the things the model actually
does are aligned
with what you want,
then does it still matter what
the model thinks internally?
I don't know.
[INAUDIBLE] if I
have the ability
to evaluate the
morality of the model?
Yeah, that's what
we're trying to do.
We're trying to make like a
really, really good evaluation
signal.
And then you can select for--
you can train the
model to do the things
that you want it to do because
you can just always evaluate.
Then the model can do stuff.
I've probably [INAUDIBLE]
that much about that.
Yeah, that's my question.
I don't think
there's [INAUDIBLE]..
But yeah, thanks so much
for the great lecture.
Very interesting.
Actually, [INAUDIBLE]
topic of ChatGPT,
I might care just to do a live
on this application thing.
Yeah, sure.
Just to end the class.
Sorry, so I'll just [INAUDIBLE].
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Give our speaker a
round of applause.